Inventory of the Klaus Kirchner collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Klaus Kirchner collection
1941-1945
2011C59
Kirchner, Klaus
5 manuscript boxes (2.0 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
World War II Soviet propaganda broadsides, leaflets and flyers, aimed at German troops and the German population.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Dr. Klaus Kirchner, a collector of propaganda, is based in Erlangen, Germany. Kirchner created a comprehensively illustrated set of reference books on World War II leaflets, flyers, pamphlets, and broadsides which was published from 1972 to 2009.
Scope and Content of Collection
The material in this collection is from Klaus Kirchner's "Soviet Central Series." It consists of World War II Soviet propaganda broadsides, leaflets, and flyers aimed at German troops and the German population. Kirchner wrote the following as an explanatory note for the collection: "The Soviet Government started to produce and disseminate aerial propaganda leaflets for Germans on June 22, 1941, the day the German Wehrmacht invaded Russia. The leaflet campaign of the 'Soviet Central Series' continued to the very last day of World War II, May 8, 1945."
All propaganda pamphlets are numbered; the pamphlet number is placed prominently at the beginning of each entry. Materials are organized by the same numerical system Kircher used in his published works. Only those numbers listed are found in the collection.
Kirchner's organizational system, translations, text selection, and notes have retained his original description. A key to the item descriptions, including number, first words printed, date, size, preservation grade, means of distribution, and description/translation, begins the container list.
Many of the items are listed or illustrated in Kirchner's books. For more details and reproductions of some "Soviet Central Series" leaflets, see Kirchner's Flugblätter aus der UdSSR, Juni-August 1941 (vol. 8), Flugblätter aus der UdSSR, September-Dezember 1941 (vol. 9), and Flugblätter aus der UdSSR: Gesamtverzeichnis der strategischen Serie: Bibliographie (vol. 14).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda.; Propaganda, Russian.
Collection Contents
- Soviet Central Series, 1941-1945; 1-5 (Box 1-5:)
  The following item list was created by Klaus Kirchner.
  Key to Kirchner's item description:
  Leaflet code - First words of leaflet text - size in cm - number of printed pages - preservation grade - month, year of first dissemination - means of dissemination by airplane, balloon, rocket, or artillery shell if required - description: [translation], image description
  Preservation grades:
  1 - Leaflet as printed and folded by producer
  2 - Leaflet slightly worn
  3 - Leaflet shows some damage
  4 - Fragment of leaflet
  - Rundfunkrede... Stalin am 3. Juli 1941..., 1941 July (Folder 1: 15)
    10x13 cm - 16 - preservation: 1, crinkling by artillery dissemination. Description: [J. W Stalin, the Soviet leader was so stunned by Hitler's invasion, it took him almost two weeks to recover from the shock that Hitler had betrayed him and to inform the Russian population that he would fight the German Wehrmacht. For the first and last time he addressed his people as brothers and sisters...]
  - Deutscher Soldat! Jetzt hast Du uns kennengelernt. Wir haben uns tapfer..., 1941 July (Folder 1: 36)
    13x19 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. description: [German soldier! Now you have met us! We fought courageously. Let us talk honestly from man to man, without reservations. You are a German, I am a Russian...].
  - GENUG MIT DEM BLINDEN VERTRAUEN! Man sagt uns, der Soldat..., 1941 July (Folder 1: 39)
    13x19 cm - 1 - preservation: 1. Description: [Enough of unconditional trust! They tell us a soldier does not have to think... Down with Hitler. A group of German soldiers].
  - SOLDAT DER DEUTSCHEN ARMEE! DU SOLLST DIE WAHRHEIT..., 1941 July (Folder 1: 54)
    12x17 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Soldier of the German Army! You should know the truth! At a conquered command post of a German regiment the Red Army had seized letters of German soldiers...]
  - GEHT MIT DIESEM PASSIERSCHEIN..., 1941 July (Folder 1: 65)
    15xl0 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: the two-language safe conduct without additional text was disseminated in 1941.
  - Nachrichten von der Front (Nr. 16) LUFTANGRIFF VON SOWJETFLUGZEUGEN AUF BERLIN..., 1941 August (Folder 1: 165)
    13x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [... Soviet airplanes are attacking Berlin... German-Fascist airplanes are bombarding positions of German troops... The German Command is afraid of soldiers' letters...].
  - Siegfried Witte,..., 1941 August (Folder 1: 196)
    1xl0 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Sergeant Siegfried Witte is writing a letter to his wife Emmi from Russian captivity…] Photograph: we see a German lance corporal (Gefreiter) writing a letter, but the leaflet describes the German soldier as a sergeant. As a result of mistakes like these the credibility of Soviet leaflets in general was damaged.
  - Deutscher Soldat! Während Du jeden Augenblick in..., 1941 August (Folder 1: 218)
    15x12 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [... While you are in danger of being killed any moment your wife and children are waiting for you at home...]. Photograph: A wife and two children are waiting.
  - Das ist die wahre Menschlichkeit…, 1941 September (Folder 1: 280)
    14x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [This is the true human love of Soviet Russia... Come on over to the side of the Red Army...] Photograph: A Russian nurse is taking good care of a German prisoner of war. Note: the retouched moustache of the German prisoner. All German prisoners of war had been shaved of all body hair. On the reverse, not shown here, a letter is reproduced of the German soldier depicted here. He had written home to his parents and his sister. Note: there was no postal service between USSR and Germany during World War II.
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 26, 1941 September (Folder 1: 283)
    13x17 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [... The Red Army has taken Jelna. ..Booty of the Red Army... The attacks of the Red Army will be continued... The 29th German motorized Division has been destroyed...].
  - Auslands-Nachrichten (Nr. 28) [News from Foreign Countries (No. 28)], 1941 September (Folder 1: 284)
    13x17 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [... The Italian people demand the end of the war and the Germans to be driven out of Italy. ..]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 17 [What is happening in Germany? No. 17], 1941 September (Folder 1: 285)
    13x16 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [... Hitler is leading Germany to a catastrophe... German women are demanding an end to the war... Pamphlets against the war... Executions and arrests... German soldiers! Join the voice of your people! Make an end to this senseless and bloody war.]
  - MACHT SCHLUSS MIT DEM KRIEG!..., 1941 September (Folder 1: 308)
    10x14 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Make an end to this war! Come over to the side of the Red Army! Comrades of the 18th Tank Division! I am now in captivity. My life is safe. I am being treated well. You all have the same wish as I: we want to make an end to this war. It is a shame for us German soldiers to make war against the workers and the peasants of Soviet Russia...]. On reverse, the Soviet standard two language safe conduct is reproduced.
  - AN DIE DEUTSCHEN OFFIZIERE Von ihren in russischer Kriegsgefangenschaft..., 1941 September (Folder 1: 339)
    15x21 cm - 4 - blue, yellow - preservation: 1. Description: [To the German officers. From their comrades in Russian captivity... Do everything you can which will bring Germany out of this hopeless war. The German Wehrmacht can only serve Germany but not the Nazis and the Gestapo...]. Eleven photographs: German officers, facsimiles of their declaration and their signatures.
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 33..., 1941 September (Folder 1: 341)
    13x17 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper "News from the Front": […Attacks of the Soviet Air Force... Russian and English airplanes are fighting together... Typhoid epidemic in the German Army...].
  - Seht Euch diese Manner an: Was sagen ihre Gesichter?..., 1941 September (Folder 1: 346)
    15x22 cm - 2 - red - preservation: 1. Description: [Look at these men - What do their faces tell? Irreconcilable hate against the enemy and invincible will for victory is visible... Russian partisans are the faithful sons of the freedom loving Russian people, they are heroes and avengers. Be aware of their hate and bullets. Partisans are everywhere and you cannot attack them...]
  - AN DIE JUGEND DER GANZEN WELT!..., 1941 September (Folder 1: 347)
    14x21 cm - 4 - preservation: 1. Description: [To the youth of the whole world! On September 28, 1941 an antifascist rally was held in Moscow...]. A German communist, Hans Mahle, was among the delegates.
  - Fragen und Antworten, die jetzt aktuell..., 1941 September (Folder 1: 354)
    13x18 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Questions and answers. Why Soviet Russia has concluded an agreement with England against Hitler-Germany? Because everybody takes all the help he can get from his neighbor if he is attacked by an enemy... It would have been stupid not to accept this help... England and Soviet Russia have a common enemy - Hitler...].
  - DIE WAHRHEIT über SOWJETRUSSLAND. Die Lügen des "Angriff" haben..., 1941 September (Folder 1: 355)
    15x23 cm - 2 - red - preservation: 1, two punch holes at the edge, no loss of text. Description: [The truth about Soviet Russia. The lies of the "Angriff" have short legs. After the unfaithful attack of Hitler on the Soviet Union the Nazi press is trying to defame the Soviet country; the mighty friend of the German people... Hands off from the mighty socialist state of workers and peasants...]
  - Ehrliche Worte eines jungen Deutschen..., 1941 September (Folder 1: 361)
    14x18 cm - 2 - preservation: 1, two punch holes. Description: [Honest words of a young German... On this rally, a young antifascist, Hans Mahle, from Hamburg said: "I, a young worker from Hamburg, I am speaking to you, German boys and girls... The Nazi murderers tell you, the German youth was born to die on the battle fields. Cynically Hitler declared he will not hesitate for one moment to sacrifice millions of Germans to reach this goal...]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 24, 1941 October (Folder 1: 370)
    13x17 cm - 2 - preservation: 1, two punch holes, no loss of text. Description: [What is happening in Germany? No. 24... German soldier! Listen to the voice of your people, they are extremely fed up with this war... At first the bombs burst and then the air-raid-alarm was sounded...].
  - Bestimmungen über Kriegsgefangene in der Sowjetunion..., 1941 October (Folder 1: 374)
    13x17 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Orders on the treatment of (German) prisoners of war... July 1, 1941... It is forbidden: a) to insult or mistreat prisoners of war...].
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 24, 1941 October (Folder 1: 375)
    13x17 cm - 2 - preservation: 1, two punch holes, no loss of text. Description of newspaper [What is happening in Germany No.24... German newspapers admit that the "Blitzkrieg" failed... Hungry Germans refuse to say "Heil Hitler" ... German pilots refuse to fly... In Germany an uprising is expected...].
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? [Nr. 25], 1941 October (Folder 1: 376)
    13x17 cm - 2 - preservation: 1, two punch holes, no loss of text. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 25... German newspapers report the failure of the "Blitzkrieg"... German pilots refuse to fly their airplanes... An uprising of the German population is expected... Machine guns are deployed on all street crossings in Berlin, Munich and other major cities...]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 36, 1941 October (Folder 1: 377)
    12x18 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 36... The Moscow conference of the major powers of the anti-Hitler coalition... As a result of this conference America and England will supply the Soviet Union with substantial amounts of weapons...]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 26, 1941 October (Folder 1: 378)
    13x17 cm - 2 - preservation: 1, two punch holes, no loss of text. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 26... German soldier! The situation at home is getting worse, hunger is cropping up, the need growing... Substantial discontent in Cologne... Unrest in Essen... Censorship is delaying soldiers mail... The ghost of Napoleon is frightening Hitler...]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 37., 1941 October (Folder 1: 379)
    13x17 cm - 2 - preservation: 1, two punch holes, no loss of text. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 37... The USA are welcoming the results of the Moscow conference... The USA and England will practically fulfill any Russian demand...]
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 36, 1941 October (Folder 1: 382)
    14x17 cm - 4 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 36... They don't want to continue...Hitler cannot supply his soldiers with trousers...And the war has just begun. How shall it end?... This is documented by the following illustration...]. Translation of reproduced document: [... Authentication! Soldier first class Weiss is allowed to use Russian uniform trousers because his trousers cannot be used anymore and his unit cannot supply him with new trousers...]
  - HITLER BELÜGT DAS DEUTSCHE VOLK. DEUTSCHER SOLDAT!..., 1941 October (Folder 1: 383)
    13x19 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Hitler is lying to the German people. German soldier! The leader of the Soviet Information Agency A.S. Schterbakow is telling the truth. On October 3, Hitler spoke on the radio... The enormous losses of the Fascist German army on the East Front are causing severe unrest and discontent...]
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 37, 1941 October (Folder 1: 388)
    13x17 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [News from the Front No. 37... U-boat "U-570" reached an English port. The German U-boat "U-570" was seized in the Atlantic and was taken to an English port on October 3...]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 28, 1941 October (Folder 1: 389)
    13x17 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [... You will never see (Leningrad)... Germany is ruled by plutocrats... Down with the inhuman Hitler! Make an end to this war. Surrender to the Red Army!]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 38, 1941 October (Folder 1: 399)
    13x17 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [... English tanks for Soviet Russia...The USA has an arsenal of weapons for the anti-Hitler block.. America is ensuring victory over Hitler in the battle for the Atlantic...]
  - Eine neue Offensive - neue Berge von Leichen Deutsche..., 1941 October (Folder 1: 401)
    14x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [A new offensive - new mountains of dead... At the beginning of the new offensive at the East Front Hitler sent you an address. Hitler is lying to you in order to drive you to a new disaster... Refuse the order to attack! Make an end to this war!].
  - Schuss mit den sinnlosen Opfern! Deutsche Soldaten!..., 1941 October (Folder 1: 403)
    14x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1, two punch holes - 10.1941- description: [In his speech on 2nd October Hitler repeated his lie that he attacked Russia because the Red Army had prepared the war against Germany... Make an end to the senseless sacrifices... Hitler will kill millions of German soldiers on the battle fields but he will not gain the rule of the world...]
  - Vier Verwundete deutsche Soldaten..., 1941 October (Folder 1: 404)
    14x20 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Four wounded German soldiers... Your officers have told you the Russians kill German prisoners and wounded... The Red Army is adhering strictly to the rules of war: No revenge is taken on prisoners! No fighting against those without weapons!...]. On reverse, a facsimile of the announcement made by the four prisoners is reproduced.
  - Briefwechsel zwischen dem Präsidenten der Vereinigten Staaten von Amerika, 1941 November (Folder 1: 447)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Exchange of letters between President Roosevelt and Comrade Stalin... I have given my agreement to send all armament (necessary). Order has been given to start delivery immediately...].
  - Deutscher Soldat! Auch Dich wird die Kugel treffen!..., 1941 November (Folder 1: 460)
    13x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1, two punch holes, no loss of text. Description: [German soldier! You also will be hit by a bullet! Hitler is driving you into another offensive. And again he tells you: "Only one last, the very last effort - and the war will be over!"... Until this offensive the German Army has already lost 4,500,000 soldiers, dead, wounded and prisoners...]
  - HITLER IST DER FEIND..., 1941 November (Folder 1: 463)
    16x25 cm - 2 - preservation: 1, two punch holes, no loss of text. Description: [Hitler is the enemy of the German people. German soldiers! You are waging war against Soviet Russia. Are the Soviet people your enemy? No!... Hitler is the enemy of the German people...]. Photomontage: Hitler himself is digging the graves for his soldiers.
  - Ein Appell deutscher Soldaten Deutsche..., 1941 November (Folder 1: 464)
    17x25 cm - 2 - preservation: 2, weathered. Description: the leaflet is a first attempt by the Soviet government to build an anti-Nazi organization among German prisoners of war in Soviet custody. [Appeal of German soldiers... Since Hitler achieved power the German people have had to keep silent. Only now, in Russian captivity, German soldiers are able to say openly what they think. Initiated by an antifascist prisoner of war, a meeting in camp 58 took place on 8th to 10th October... 158 soldiers from different sections of life participated... The German people does not have to rule foreign countries but it should be ruling its own country.]
  - DER WEG ZUM FRIEDEN UND ZUR RÜCKKEHR IN DIE HEIMAT..., 1941 November (Folder 1: 469)
    16x26 cm - 2 - preservation: 1, two punch holes, no loss of text. Description: [The way to peace and to returning home... You have the weapons in your hands...]. Photomontage: dead German soldier and tank in snow. Photograph: German prisoners of war at work.
  - Wie ist dem Krieg ein Ende zu..., 1941 November (Folder 1: 470)
    14x21cm - 2 - preservation: 1, punch holes, no loss of text. Description, see also above leaflet code 463: [How to make an end to this war...The appeal was signed by 158 soldiers from different sections of life...]. Photomontage: German prisoners of war sign the appeal of the "158."
  - SEIDE UND LÄUSE..., 1941 November (Folder 1: 481)
    13x22 cm - 2 - red - preservation: 1, punch holes, no loss of text. Description: [Silk and lice. In every German town women can now be seen, their eyes red with tears their husbands have been killed in front of Moscow, Leningrad or Rostov. They also dream of ham, a fur coat, silk stockings. Only lice eat from your frozen bodies...]. The author of the text was Ilia Erenburg.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 35, 1941 November (Folder 1: 491)
    14x21 cm - 2 - red - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 35. Goebbels is talking about a possible defeat of Germany... Nazi lies to intimidate the people. The Nazi-press is spreading the lie that the enemies of Germany are intending to sterilize all German men... Hitler began his rule by sterilization of the Jews...]
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 39, 1941 November (Folder 1: 492)
    15x23 cm - 2 - red - preservation: 1, two punch holes, no loss of text. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 39... The German Wehrmacht has lost 6 million men... Big English offensive in Libya... The Russian winter is just beginning... The dead bodies of frozen German soldiers...]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 43, 1941 December (Folder 1: 493)
    14x21 cm - 2 - paper: red - preservation: 1, two punch holes, no loss of text. Description of leaflet newspaper [News from foreign countries No. 43: The USA has abolished the neutrality act... The USA will transport war material under armed protection to ports of countries fighting against Hitler-Germany... American troops in Dutch Guyana...]
  - DEUTSCHER SOLDAT, DER RUSSISCHE WINTER IST DEIN TOD..., 1941 December (Folder 1: 495)
    13x23 cm - 2 - red - preservation: 1. Description: [German soldier, the Russian winter will be your death... Nothing but cold and death...] Photomontage
  - Das deutsche Nachrichtenbüro über den Verlust von Rostow..., 1941 December (Folder 1: 508)
    13x20 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1, two punch holes, no loss of text. Description: [The German news-agency on the loss of Rostov... Lies have short legs...]
  - Kameraden der 23. Infanterie-Division! Als in der Nacht zum 30. August..., 1941 December (Folder 1: 510)
    13x20 cm - 2 - red - preservation: 1, two punch holes, no loss of text. Description: [Comrades of the 23rd Infantry Division!... Why should I as a worker kill other workers?...]
  - Kameraden an der Front! Zu Euch spricht..., 1941 December (Folder 1: 511)
    13x20 cm - 2 - red - preservation: 1. Description: a German POW is describing life in Soviet captivity. [Comrades at the front!..]
  - IN DEN KÄMPFEN VOR MOSKAU..., 1941 December (Folder 1: 514)
    14x20 cm - 2 - green - preservation: 1, punch holes, no loss of text. Description: [During the fighting in front of Moscow already 600,000 Germans have lost their lives... Hitler demanded in one of his orders that Moscow should be captured at any price... The Russians will not give up Moscow at any price... Soldier do not shoot at Russian soldiers!...].
  - MIT HITLER WIRD NIEMAND FRIEDEN..., 1941 December (Folder 1: 516)
    14x22 cm - 2 - green- preservation: 1. Description: [Nobody will make peace with Hitler... Hitler and his clique have shown themselves as Imperialists...]
  - Nachrichten von der Front Nr. 42, 1941 December (Folder 1: 524)
    15x24 cm - 2 - red - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the From No. 42... Panic-like retreat of Germans in the South... The USA are producing weapons for the war in the air...]. Caption of photograph: [One of the many American airplanes in Soviet Russia]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 44, 1941 December (Folder 1: 525)